William Langner Papers
William Langner Papers
1935-1996
Langner, William R.
94 linear ft.
William Langner worked for the Department of Education's Division of Adult Education and Literacy for many years. He was active in raising awareness of education for the disabled (Langner himself was a paraplegic from the age of 18 due to a car accident). Collection includes correspondence (both personal and professional), writings, memorabilia, and large amounts of printed material (papers, reports, handbooks, manuals, etc).concerning adult education.
2587183
Biographical History
William Langner (1932-1998) was born in Morrisville, New York. He attended Morrisville-Eaton Central Schools and, after a family move, graduated from Henry Clay High School in Ashland, Virginia. During his freshman year at the College of William and Mary, while hitchhiking south to Florida for spring break, he was involved in a car accident which left him paralyzed from the waist down. He spent nearly two years in the hospital after which, undaunted, he enrolled at the University of Virginia where he earned a bachelor's degree in economics in 1957.
Despite his qualifications, Langner struggled for several years to support himself with a series of jobs including advance sales for circuses, advertising sales, owner/operator of an import/export business (Langner and Company), and teacher at the Blue Ridge School in St. George, Virginia. In the early 1960s he served on the Board of Directors of Cordet Foundation, a Richmond, Virginia job training program that specialized in finding employment for the disabled, and in 1964 he opened Commonwealth Tutoring Center in Richmond. Over the next decade Commonwealth Tutoring and its successor organizations -- Educational Development Center (1966?-1970) and Langner Learning Center (1970-1978) -- served hundreds of students from the local school districts as well as offering foreign languages and other training to local executives.
In addition to operating his tutoring schools, Langner served on the Virginia Board of Vocational Rehabilitation, the Governor's Commission on Employment of the Handicapped, the Mayor's Committee on the Handicapped, and the board of directors of numerous social and civic organizations including the local branches of Easter Seals and Goodwill. In 1973, President Nixon appointed him to the National Advisory Council on Adult Education (NACAE) where he served for three years. He received an M.Ed. from Virginia Commonwealth University in 1977 and was an adjunct faculty member there for two years (1977-1979). He also worked as an educational consultant to various business, governmental, and educational institutions. Langner also traveled several times to Central and South America which stimulated a lifelong interest in the region.
Persistent cash flow problems due to old and new medical expenses and intermittent hospitalizations had for years prevented Langner from achieving any kind of financial security, but that came at last in 1980 with an offer of a position with the Department of Health, Education and Welfare (HEW). When the Department of Education was split off from HEW, Langner took a position with new department's Division of Adult Education and Literacy (DAEL). While with the Department of Education, he implemented the National Adult Literacy and Learning Disability Center (NALLDC) and was instrumental in organizing the Clearing House on Adult Education and Literacy, which compiled, wrote, and published fact sheets, pamplets, guides, directories, bibliographies, newsletters and other resource material.
Langner was a member of the National GED Advisory Committee from 1981 to 1987 and worked with the GED Testing Service to train test administrators. He participated in the White House Adult Literacy Initiative (1983) and was on the advisory committee for the International Center for the Disabled's "Survey III," and served as advisory board member for the University of the District of Columbia Department of Adult Education. With Boris Bogatz of Gallaudet College, he organized a National Congress for Adults with Special Learning Needs in 1987, which resulted in several annual conferences and grew into the National Association for Adults with Special Learning Needs (NAASLN), and he coordinated the first World Congress for Adult Learners with Disabilities in 1995.
Langner was a founding member of the American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE) and chair of its Adult Learners with Disabilities Unit. He was a member of the International Council for Adult Education (ICAE) and served on the executive committee of its International Associates, and under its sponsorship coordinated the International Network for Adult Learners with Disabilities. He was a delegate to the World Assembly of Adult Education three times and during his career received nearly a dozen awards for his work in education of the disabled. In addition to his professional activities, he was a Freemason, a Rotarian, a member of the education honor society Kappa Delta Psi, traveled extensively, and opened his home to eleven foster sons over the years.
Langner retired from the Department of Education in 1995, intending to purchase a small farm in Florida or Belize. He died in 1998.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The William Langner Papers spans nearly sixty years and includes correspondence (both personal and professional), writings, memorabilia, and large amounts of printed material (papers, reports, handbooks, manuals, etc) relating to adult education. The collection illuminates the growth of interest in adult education of the disabled both at the federal level and at the state and local level. In addition, the large and comprehensive quantity of personal material, spanning Langner's entire life, highlights Langner's refusal to be discouraged or hindered by his disability and illuminates the challenges faced by the disabled during this period. Throughout his life, as the collection amply demonstrates, Langner exhibited impressive perseverance, drive, and integrity; despite recurrent illnesses due in large part to his paraplegia, he not only worked full-time but raised eleven foster sons over the years and traveled to more than thirty foreign countries -- including a trip to the Amazon which required his wheelchair be lashed to poles and carried through the jungle on the shoulders of native guides.
Biographical and personal material contains material relating to Langner's personal life, including correspondence with family and friends; correspondence with and records relating to several of Langner's foster sons; bills and other material from Langner's creditors over the years; various potential business ventures; medical records; resumes and biographical sketches along with genealogical material on the Langner and Rankin families; membership information for clubs to which Langner belonged; and books, brochures, clippings, maps, newsletters and reference material on Langner's two main avocations: tropical agriculture and travel. Included here is a letter Langner received from "The Seven Society," the most secretive of the University of Virginia's secret societies and known for its generosity. The letter was accompanied by a gift of money to help defray Langner's expenses while attending the University.
Correspondence-subject files comprise the bulk of the collection, and the largest subset of this material (27 boxes) is that from Langner's years at the the Department of Education. This includes vast amounts of internal correspondence as well as weekly work reports, site visit reports, Langner's job performance evaluations, and Sections 310 and 353 grant applications and projects. (See Printed material below for additional Department of Education material.) Other topics or organizations with a significant amount of material include the American Association of Adult and Continuing Education (6 boxes), the GED Advisory Committee (4 boxes), the International Council for Adult Education (ICAE) (5 boxes), Langner Learning Center (8 boxes), National Advisory Council on Adult Education (6 boxes), and the National Association for Adults with Special Learning Needs (NAASLN) (6 boxes).
Memorabilia contains certificates, clippings, letters of appreciation and thanks, Langner's passports, photographs (of Langner and of others), a collection of postcards, and miscellaneous souvenirs.
Multimedia consists of three multimedia programs (videotape with accompanying literature), several floppy disks (some commercial and some Langner's), and two audiocassettes.
Printed material consists of reports, papers, summaries, conference proceedings, newsletters, books, brochures, journals and other material on various topics relating to adult education. Topics include adult basic education, the Adult Education Act, the Americans with Disabilities Act, competency-based adult education, correctional education, the GED, international education, education of the learning disabled, literacy, and miscellaneous books, journals and newsletters. Also included here are four boxes of reports, papers, and other printed material from the Department of Education.
The last series, Writings, contains Langner's own writings and spans much of his career. Included here are numerous issues of two newsletters written and edited by Langner while at the Department of Education ("Adult learning activities" and "Adult learning seminars"), drafts and outlines for Langner's work on two books for Cowles Book Company's GED preparatory series, and typescripts of articles, papers, speeches, and presentations, including a few that offer personal reflections on his disability. Also included here are several notebooks, many outlines and fragments of pieces, and an assortment of miscellany (to do lists, notes, reminders, and other scraps).
Arrangement of the Collection
Material in all series are arranged alphabetically. For material that required subdivision, most are alphabetical but some (e.g. Langner Learning Center, Department of Education) are arranged chronologically to provide a more narrative structure.
Related Material
The library holds a considerable number of collections related to adult and continuing education. Please refer to for a complete listing of all adult education collections.
Separated Material
The collection originally included a considerable number of books and journals. Books that were duplicates of items already held by or in the circulating collection of the library were discarded. For journals which were already held by the library, duplicate issues were discarded; issues the library did not have were sent to Periodicals for cataloging (these are annotated in the catalog as "Gift of William Langner"). Journals which were not held by the library remained with the collection and may be found in Printed material: Misc journals (Box 146).
Subject and Genre Headings
Adult education; Langner, William R.; American Association for Adult and Continuing Education.; GED Testing Service (Center for Adult Learning and Educational Credentials); International Council for Adult Education.; National Advisory Council on Adult Education (U.S.); National Association for Adults with Special Learning Needs.; United States. -- Department of Education.; United States. -- Division of Adult Education and Literacy.; Adult education -- United States.; Educators -- United States.; Elementary education of adults.; People with disabilities -- Education -- United States.; People with disabilities -- Legal status, laws, etc. -- United States.; Special education.; Audiocassettes.; Books.; Brochures.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Manuscripts (document genre); Minutes (administrative records); Newsletters.; Periodicals.; Photographs.; Postcards.; Proceedings.; Reports.; Videocassettes.; Educators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Gift of William R. Langner.
Inventory
- Biographical and personal material
  - —, Han (Box 1)
  - —, Kecha (Box 1)
  - —, Peggy (Box 1)
  - 2709 Chamberlayne Avenue, house in Richmond (Box 1)
  - Agriculture
    - Florida (Box 1)
    - Tropical (Box 1)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - Amway (Box 2)
  - Arizona State University (Box 2)
  - Belize, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Berthelette, Mike (foster son), 2 folders (Box 2)
  - "Bill Page Honda" (Box 2)
  - Birds and birdwatching (Box 2)
  - Board, Sally Ann (Box 2)
  - "Books to order" (Box 3)
  - Bookstore, info on starting a bookstore (Box 3)
  - Boomerangs (Box 3)
  - Business opportunities, specialty foods, franchises, etc (Box 3)
  - Cards, greeting, Christmas, birthday, get-well; 5 folders (Box 3, 4)
  - Chork, Hong (foster son) (Box 4)
  - Colgate University (Box 4)
  - College of William and Mary (Box 4)
  - Creditors, miscellaneous, 8 folders (Box 4, 5, 6)
  - Deal, Willis R. (Box 6)
  - Dictionary of International Biography (Box 6)
  - Emory, Lloyd (foster son) (Box 6)
  - Explorers Club (Box 6)
  - Family
    - —, Abbie (aunt?) (Box 6)
    - —, Hertha (aunt) (Box 6)
    - Bowman family, Carol (sister) and Graham; Paige and Courtney (Box 6)
    - Francisco family, Donna (sister) and Waddy; Bonnie, Donna Brooke, Jeff, Michael, Peter (Box 7)
    - Langner, — (grandfather) (Box 7)
    - Langner, Helen and Herbert (parents) (Box 7)
    - Rankin, Effie (grandmother) (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 7)
  - Financial and legal papers, bank statements, loans, wills, insurance, etc.; 7 folders (Box 7, 8, 9)
  - Florida (Box 9)
  - Foster parenting, miscellaneous (Box 9)
  - Globe Trotters Club (Box 9)
  - Grammer, Ron (foster son) (Box 9)
  - Great Expeditions (Box 9)
  - Greenlaw, Bill (Box 9)
  - Henry (dog), includes letters to/from First Dog C.Fred (Bush) (Box 9)
  - Henry Clay High School (Box 9)
  - Horowitz, Inge and Harold (Box 9)
  - Import/export business, 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Investments (Box 10)
  - José (bird) (Box 10)
  - Keiningham, Jean and Tom, also includes material from their son Tom, who was one of Langner's foster sons (Box 10)
  - Lipscomb, Francis ("Buddy) (foster son) (Box 10)
  - "Mail order" (Box 10)
  - Masons (Freemasons), includes issues of Scottish Rite journal; 2 folders (Box 10)
  - Mayer, Thomasia D. (Box 10)
  - Medical papers, bills, prescriptions, diagnoses, reports, correspondence, health insurance, etc; 8 folders (Box 11, 12)
  - Moore, Tommy (foster son) (Box 13)
  - Morrisville-Eaton Central Schools, 1939-1946 (Box 13)
  - Munro, Connie (Box 13)
  - National Enquirer, clipping, correspondence regarding Langner's Amazon trip (Box 13)
  - Nixon's speech in Los Angeles, 1955 (Box 13)
  - Ouk, Mon (foster son) (Box 13)
  - Owen, Ed (Box 13)
  - Phan Sam (adopted son), 4 folders (Box 13)
  - Pok Dul (foster son) (Box 14)
  - "Real Estate" (Box 14)
  - "Regan Inaugration" (Box 14)
  - Resumes and biographical sketches (Box 14)
  - "Retirement" (Box 14)
  - Rotary Club, includes "Tabasco" and "Progress" newsletters; 3 folders (Box 14)
  - Scott, S. Buford (Box 15)
  - The Seven Society (Box 15)
  - Social Security (Box 15)
  - Sothy, Phurkimony ("Sam") (foster son) (Box 15)
  - South American Explorers Club (Box 15)
  - St. John's Church (Box 15)
  - St. Paul's Church (Box 15)
  - Teacher's College, Columbia University (Box 15)
  - "To Do - 1992" (Box 15)
  - Travel
    - Africa (Box 15)
    - Africa, oversize (Box 162)
    - Asia (Box 15)
    - Europe (Box 16)
    - North America (Box 16)
    - Oceania (Box 16)
    - South America (Box 16)
    - Miscellaneous, newsletters, brochures, catalogs, eco-tourism, etc; 2 folders (Box 17)
  - Trimmer, Edward ("Country") (foster son) (Box 17)
  - University of Illinois (Box 17)
  - University of Toronto (Box 17)
  - University of Virginia (Box 17)
  - Washington Symphony Orchestra (Box 18)
  - Miscellaneous, 7 folders (Box 18, 19)
- Correspondence-subject files
  - ABE Institute, 1994 (Box 20)
  - Academic Therapy Publications (Box 20)
  - Adkins Life Skills Program (Box 20)
  - Adult Basic and Literacy Education, Pennsylvania (ABLE), includes "Focus on…" newsletters; 2 folders (Box 20)
  - Adult Education Association of Virginia (Box 20)
  - Adult Education Research Conference (Box 20)
  - Africa Study Tour, See Ontario Institute of for Studies in Education (OISE).
  - African Development Foundation (Box 20)
  - Agency for International Development (Box 20)
  - Ali, Patricia (Box 20)
  - Alpha Kappa Psi (Box 20)
  - American Association for Adult and Continuing Education (AAACE)
    - Correspondence, 1969-1981; 3 folders (Box 20)
    - Correspondence, 1982-1985; 5 folders (Box 21)
    - Correspondence, 1986-1994; 1998,; undated; 7 folders (Box 22)
    - Adult Learners With Disabilities Unit (Box 23)
    - Board meetings, 1984; 1985,; 1990; 3 folders (Box 23)
    - Conferences, 1972-1977; 1979,; 1980-1984; 5 folders (Box 24)
    - Conferences, 1985-1992; 1994; 3 folders (Box 24)
    - Constitution and bylaws (Box 24)
    - Directories and rosters, 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Newsletters, 1974-1976; 1983-1987; 2 folders (Box 24)
    - Newsletters, 1987-1997; 3 folders (Box 25)
    - Policies and procedures (Box 25)
    - Reports and papers, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 25)
  - American Association for Higher Education (AAHE) (Box 26)
    See also Heath Resource Center.
  - American Council on Education, includes "Higher Education and National Affairs" newsletter (Box 26)
    See also GED Advisory Committee and Printed material: Newsletters: G (GED Items, GED Profiles, GED Research Briefs).
  - American Council on Rural Special Education (ACRES) (Box 26)
  - American Foundation for the Blind (Box 26)
  - American Jail Association (Box 26)
  - American Library Association (Box 26)
  - American Optometric Association (Box 26)
  - American Society of Association Executives (ASAE), 2 folders (Box 26)
  - American Society for Training and Development (ASTD) (Box 26)
  - American Vocational Association (Box 26)
  - Assault on Illiteracy Program (AOIP) (Box 26)
  - Association for Children with Learning Disabilities (ACLD), include "ACLD Newsbriefs" newsletter; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Association for Community-Based Education (ACBE) (Box 27)
  - Association for Continuing Higher Education (ACHE), includes "Five Minutes with ACHE" newsletter; 2 folders (Box 27)
  - Axford, Roger (Box 27)
  - Barrow, Nita (Dame) (Box 27)
  - Baughman, Fred A. (Box 27)
  - Baum, Charlene (Box 27)
  - Beacon College (Box 27)
  - Berk, Neal (circus promoter) (Box 27)
  - Berlitz School of Languages (Box 27)
  - Blaise, Charles, See Optometric Extension Program.
  - Blue Ridge School (Box 27)
  - Brightman, Sam (Box 27)
  - Buscaglia, Leo, photocopy of letter (Box 28)
  - Bush, George and Barbara (Box 28)
    See also Biographical and personal material: Henry (dog)
  - Business Council for Effective Literacy, includes 2 folders of "Adult literacy: Programs, planning, issues" newsletter; 3 folders (Box 28)
  - California Adult Student Assessment System (CASAS) (Box 28)
  - Cambodia and Cambodian refugees, 3 folders (Box 28)
  - Canadian Association for Adult Education (Box 28)
  - Carter, Jimmy (Box 28)
  - Cash, Johnny (Box 28)
  - Cassara, Beverly (Box 28)
  - Center for the Study of Liberal Education for Adults (CSLEA), includes "Continuing Education for Adults" newsletter; 2 folders (Box 28)
  - Central Virginia Society for Children with Specific Learning Disabilities (Box 29)
  - Charters, Alexander N. (Box 29)
  - Clearinghouse of Resources for Educators of Adults (CREA), See Syracuse University.
  - Cleveland Clinic (Box 29)
  - Clyde Beatty-Cole Bros. Circus (Box 29)
  - Coalition of Adult Education Organizations (CAEO), 3 folders (Box 29)
  - Coalition of Lifelong Learning Organizations (COLLO) (Box 29)
  - J.F. Coates (publisher) (Box 29)
  - Commission on Adult Basic Education (COABE), 4 folders (Box 30)
  - Commission on Educational Credit and Credentials, 1983; 1990; 3 folders (Box 30)
  - Commission on Educational Credit and Credentials, 1991; 1993; 4 folders (Box 31)
  - Commission of Professors of Adult Education (CPAE) (Box 31)
  - Commonwealth Tutoring, See Langner Learning Center.
  - Comprehensive Adult Student Assessment System (CASAS) (Box 31)
  - CONFINTEA III (Tokyo), 1972 (Box 31)
  - CONFINTEA V (Hamburg), 1997 (Box 31)
  - Continuing Education Council (CEC) (Box 32)
  - Continuing Education Institute (CEI), 2 folders (Box 32)
  - Continuing education unit (Box 32)
  - Corcoran, John (Box 32)
  - Cordet Foundation, 9 folders (Box 32, 33)
  - Corporation for Public Broadcasting, 2 folders (Box 33, 34)
  - Correctional Education Association (CEA) (Box 34)
  - Council of Chief State School Officers (Box 34)
  - Council for Exceptional Children (CEC) (Box 34)
  - Council for Non-Collegiate Continuing Education, includes "Growing Edge" newsletter (Box 34)
    See also Continuing Education Council.
  - Cowles Book Company (Box 34)
  - Cretella, Jay, See National Association for Adults with Special Learning Needs (NAASLN) and Wallingford Adult Education.
  - Cristiani-Wallace Bros. Circus (Box 34)
  - Cumberland Hardwoods, includes "Cumberland Tree-bune" newsletter (Box 34)
  - Dalton, John W. (governor of Virginia) (Box 34)
  - Database searches and bibliographies, 6 folders (Box 34, 35)
  - DeMent, Gloria and Stoney (Box 35)
  - Department of Education
    - [General], 1967-1968 (Box 35)
    - [General], 1970-1977; 3 folders (Box 35)
    - [General], 1978-1981; 7 folders (Box 36)
    - [General], 1982-1983; 6 folders (Box 37)
    - [General], 1983; includes National Employ the Handicapped Week planning committee; 2 folders (Box 38)
    - [General], 1984; 7 folders (Box 38, 39)
    - [General], 1985; 5 folders (Box 39, 40)
    - [General], 1986; 4 folders (Box 40, 41)
    - [General], 1987; 5 folders (Box 41, 42)
    - Area IV Workshop, 1987 (Feb) (Box 42)
    - D.C. Monitoring visit, 1987 (Apr) (Box 42)
    - Weekly work reports, 1987 (Box 42)
    - [General], 1988; 4 folders (Box 42, 43)
    - Illinois site visit, 1988 (May) (Box 43)
    - Missouri monitoring visit, 1988 (Apr) (Box 43)
    - "National task force focusing on adult learners / older Americans", 1988 (Box 43)
    - Weekly work reports, 1988 (Box 43)
    - [General], 1989; 5 folders (Box 43, 44)
    - Weekly work reports, 1989 (Box 44)
    - "Technical assistance logs", 1989-1990 (Box 44)
    - [General], 1990; 9 folders (Box 45, 46)
    - Compliance review reports, 1990 (Box 47)
    - Weekly work reports, 1990 (Box 47)
    - [General], 1991; 9 folders (Box 47, 48, 49)
    - Compliance review reports, 1991 (Box 49)
    - Weekly work reports, 1991 (Box 49)
    - [General], 1992; 6 folders (Box 49, 50)
    - Adults with disabilities session, 1992 (Box 50)
    - NY/New England symposium, 1992 (Box 50)
    - State directors conference, 1992 (Box 50)
    - Weekly work reports, 1992 (Box 50)
    - Wyoming site visit, 1992 (Box 50)
    - [General], 1993; 6 folders (Box 51, 52)
    - DAEL priorities, 1993 (Box 52)
    - Weekly work reports, 1993 (Box 52)
    - Welfare reform task force, 1993 (Box 52)
    - [General], 1994; 5 folders (Box 52, 53)
    - Weekly work reports, 1994 (Box 53)
    - "WV corr.", 1994 (Box 53)
    - "Work group on the recruitment, advancement, and access for people with disabilities", 1994 (Box 54)
    - [General], 1995 (Box 54)
    - ETS meeting, 1995 (Box 54)
    - [General], 1996 (Box 54)
    - [General], 1997 (Box 54)
    - [General], 1998 (Box 54)
    - "Abstracts / annotated Bib / corr. Adult literacy" (Box 54)
    - Accessible Computer Technology (ACT) VI conference (Box 54)
    - 310 and 353 projects, 12 folders (Box 55, 56)
    - Adult secondary education (Box 57)